So now we're gonna look at a very general
paradigm called the Merkle-Damgard
现在我们要看一个非常通用的机制，叫做Merkle-Damgard机制
paradigm, that's used for constructing
collision-resistant hash functions. Before
用于组建抗碰撞的哈希函数
we do that, let me just remind you what
our goals are. So as usual we say that H
在这之前，让我提醒一下我们的目标
is a hash function that maps some large
message space into a small tag space. And
通常情况下，我们说H是个哈希函数，将大的信息空间映射到小的标签空间
we say that a collision for a hash
function is basically a pair of distinct
我们说哈希函数的一个碰撞是一对不同的信息
messages that happen to map to the same
value under this hash function. And our
它们正好被哈希函数映射到同样的值
goal is to build collision-resistant hash
functions namely functions where it's hard
我们的目标是构建一个很难找到一个碰撞的抗碰撞的哈希函数
to find even a single collision. Even
though we know many collisions exist. No
尽管我们知道有很多碰撞存在
efficient algorithm can even output a
single collision. So we're gonna construct
没有有效的算法可以输出哪怕一个碰撞。那么我们要构建这些哈希函数
these hash functions, these collision
resistant hash functions, in two steps.
我们分两步构造这些抗碰撞的哈希函数
The first step, which we're gonna do in
this segment, is to show that if you give
第一步，就是我们本节要讲的，它将展示如果
me a collision resistant hash function for
short messages, we can extend it and build
你给我一个处理短信息的抗碰撞的哈希函数，我们可以扩展它
a collision resistant hash function for
much, much, much longer messages. In the
来构建一个处理长的多的信息的抗碰撞的哈希函数
next segment, we'll actually build
collision-resistant HASH functions for
在下一节，我们将构建处理短信息的抗碰撞的哈希函数。
short messages. Okay so let's look at the
construction. The construction is actually
那我们来看这个机制
very general and in fact all
collision-resistant hash functions follow
这个机制很通用，事实上，所有的抗碰撞的哈希函数
this paradigm. It's actually a very
elegant paradigm and let me show you how
都遵循这个机制。这是一个非常优雅的机制，让我来告诉你它怎样工作
it works. So here we have our function H
which we're gonna assume is a
这里我们有函数H，我们假设它是抗碰撞的哈希函数
collision-resistant hash function for
small sized inputs. So the way we're gonna
可以处理短输入
use this little function h, this h is
sometimes called a compression function,
我们使用这个小函数h，h有时叫做压缩函数
is we're gonna take a big message M and
break this message in to blocks. And then
我们将取长信息M，把它分成若干组
we use a fixed value called the IV. Here
is the case the IV is fixed forever. And
然后我们使用一个固定值叫做Ⅳ。这里Ⅳ永远是固定的
it's basically embedded in the code and in
the standards, it's just a fixed ID that's
它内嵌在代码和标准里，只是一个固定的ID
part of the fin-nation of the function.
And then what we do is we apply the small
是函数的一部分。然后我们对第一个信息分组应用
compression function H to the first
message block along with this ID. What
小的压缩函数H，一并使用这个ID
comes out of that is what's called a
chaining variable that's gonna be fed into
得到的叫做链接变量，将被交给下一压缩函数
the next compression function which
compresses the next block along with the
来压缩下一个分组，一并使用前一个链接变量
previous chaining variable and out comes
the next chaining variable, and the next
输出下一个链接变量
message block is compresses, and so on and
so forth until we which the final message
然后下个信息分组被压缩，等等，直到我们到达最后分组
block And then the final message block,
the one special thing that we do, is that
在最后分组上，我们要做一个特别的事情
we must append this padding block, this
PB, which stands for padding block (and
就是我们必须将这个补齐分组PB附在信息后面
I'll explain what the padding block is in
just a second). But after we append the
我们稍后解释这个这个补齐分组。但在我附上补齐分组之后
padding block we again compress the last
[inaudible] variable with the last message
我们还是要压缩最后的链接变量与最后的分组
block, and the output of that is the
actual output of the hash function. So
得到的输出就是实际哈希函数的输出
just to summarize, in symbols, we have
this compression function that elements in
总结一下，用符号表示，我们用这个压缩函数在T中取元素
T. This is the opposite of the hash
function. Plus message blocks, this x
这与哈希函数正好相反
corresponds to message blocks, and outputs
the next chaining variables. So as I said,
加上信息分组，这个X对应信息分组，输出下一链接变量
this is what the compression functions do.
And then from this compression function
如我所说，这就是压缩函数的工作。然后根据这个压缩函数
we're able to build a hash function for
large inputs, namely inputs is the space x
我们可以构建一个长输入的哈希函数
to some power of l namely up to l blocks
of x. And of course these are variable
输入是空间X的L次方，表示至多L^X的分组。当然这些长度可变
lengths so we could have different length
messages that are being given input to
这样我们可以有不同的信息长度
this function h and what comes out of it
is basically a tag in tag space. So the
它们给函数h输入，得到的是标签空间中的标签
only thing left to define is the padding
block. So the padding block is actually
唯一剩下的需要定义的是补齐分组
very important as we're gonna see in just
a minute. What it is, is basically, well
补齐分组非常重要，我们接下来会看到
it's a sequence of 1000 that denotes the
end of the actual message block. And then
这是序列1000，为实际明文分组的结尾
the most important part of the message
block is that we encode the message length
这个分组最重要的部分是我们对信息长度进行的编码
In this padding block. And the message
length field is basically fixed to be 64
在这个补齐分组里。信息长度域固定为64位
bits. So in all the [inaudible] hash
functions, so in all the [inaudible] hash
所以在所有的SHA哈希函数中
functions the maximum message length is
two to the sixty four minus one so in fact
最大的信息长度为2^64-1
the message length fits into a 64 bit
block. An upper bound of two to the sixty
事实上信息长度应当适应于64位分组。2^64-1位的信息长度的上界
four minus one bit on the message length
is actually sufficiently long to handle
对应我们能释放的信息来说足够长了
all of the messages we're gonna throw at
it. Okay, so that's the padding block, and
好，这是补齐分组
of course the question is: what do we do
if the last block really is a multiple of
当然，那么问题来了，如果最后一个分组
the compression function of block length?
Where are we gonna fit the padding block?
是压缩函数分组长度的倍数，我们该怎么办？我们该如何补齐分组？
And the answer, as usual, is basically if
there's no space for the padding block in
通常，答案是如果在最后分组中没有空间
the last block of the message, then we're
gonna have to ass another dummy block and
留给补齐分组时，那么我们就必须加另外一个假分组
stick the padding block in there. And of
course put the one zero, zero, zero in the
把补齐分组放在那里。当然以正确的方式写1000
right place. Okay so the point is that
it's very, very important that the padding
有一点非常重要，那就是
block contains the message length as we'll
see in just a minute. So this is the
补齐分组包含信息长度，我们待会将会看到
Merkle-Damgard construction, the last
piece of terminology I'll say is that we
那么这就是Merkle-Damgard机制，最后一点技术内容
have these chaining variables. So H0 is
the initial value. H1, H2, H3, up to H4
是我们有这些链接变量。那么HO是初始值，H1，H2，H3直到H4
which is the actual final output of this
hash function. So as I said, all standard
H4是哈希函数的最终输出。如我所说
hash functions follow this paradigm for
constructing a collision resistant hash
所有的标准哈希函数都遵循着这个机制，由一个压缩函数构建抗碰撞的哈希函数
function from a compression function. The
reason that this paradigm is so popular is
这个机制如此流行的原因是
because of the following theorem, which
says basically that if the little
因为下面这个定理告诉我们
compression function is collision
resistant, then the big Merkle-Damgard
如果小的压缩函数是抗碰撞的
hash function is also collision resistant.
So, in other words, if we're going to build
那么大的 Merkle-Damgard哈希函数也是抗碰撞的
collision resistant functions for large inputs, all
we have to do is just build compression
换句话说，如果我们要为长输入构建抗碰撞的哈希函数
functions that are collision resistant. So
let's prove this theorem. It's a elegant
我们只需构建一个抗碰撞的压缩函数。那么我们来证明这个定理
proof and it's not too difficult. So the
way we're gonna prove it is using the
这个证明很优雅，且不难，我们证明它的逆否命题
contrapositive, that is, if you can find
me a collision on the big hash function
也就是，如果你能找到这个大哈希函数的一个碰撞
then we're gonna deduce a collision on the
little compression function. Therefore, if
那么我们我们可以推出这个小压缩函数的一个碰撞
little h is a collision resistant, so will
be the big H. So suppose you give me a
因此，如果h是抗碰撞的，那么H也是
collision on the big compression function,
namely two distinct messages M and M',
假设给我一个大压缩函数的碰撞，即两个不同的信息M和M'
that happen to hash to the same output,
we're going to use M and M' to build
它们正好被哈希到同一个输出，我们将使用M和M'
a collision on the little compression
function. So the first thing is we
来构建这个小压缩函数的一个碰撞
have to remember how the Merkle-Damgard
construction works and, in particular,
首先我们必须记住 Merkle-Damgard机制的过程
let's assign names to the chain variables
when we hash M versus when we hash M'.
特别的，当我们哈希M和M'，给链接变量起一些名字
So here are the chain variables that come up
when we hash the message M, so H0 is the
当我们计算信息M的哈希值时，会得到这些链接变量
fixed IV that starts the whole process, H1
would be the result of hashing the first
那么H0是固定的Ⅳ，开启整个过程，H1是用Ⅳ计算第一个分组的哈希结果，等等
message block with the IV, and so on and
so forth, until H sub t+1 is the
直到H_t+1是最后一个链接变量
final chain variable, which is the final
output of the Merkle-Damgard chain. And
也是Merkle-Damgard链的最后输出
then similarly for M', let's define H0'
to be the first chaining variable, H1'
类似的对于M',定义H0'为第一个链接变量
to be the result after compressing
the first message block of M', and so
H1'是第一个分组M'的压缩结果，等等……
on and so forth, up until we get to H'
of r+1, which is the final hash of
直到我们获得H'_r+1,，即信息M'的最后哈希值
the message M'. Now you notice the
length of the messages M and M'
现在大家注意信息M和M'的长度
don't have to be the same. In particular, M
has length t, whereas M' has length r.
不一定是一样的。特别的，M的长度为t，M'的长度为r
Now because the collision occurred, we
know that these two values here are the
由于发生了碰撞，我们知道这两个值是相等的
same. H(M) is equal to H(M'). In
other words, the last chaining variables
H（M）是等于H(M').换句话说，最后的链接变量是
are actually equal to one another. So now
let's look carefully how H t+1 and
是等于另一个的。现在让我们仔细观察
H' r+1 were calculated. Well
H t+1 is calculated as the
H t+1和H' r+1是怎样算出来的
compression function applied to the
previous chaining variable along with the
H t+1 是由压缩函数应用到之前的的链接变量和最后分组得到的M得到的
last message block of M, including the
padding block. You'll notice here I'm
包括补白区块。大家注意
assuming that the padding block fits with
the last message block of M even if the
这里假设补白区块符合最后的分组M，即使
last padding block is in its own block,
it's not going to make any difference. So
最后补白区块在它自己的分组，也没有任何区别
for simplicity, let's assume that the
padding block fits with the last message
为了简便，我们假设补白区块在最后的分组M中，
block with capital M. So, by hashing the
last message block with a padding block
因此，通过计算放着补白区块的最后分组的和最后一个链接变量的哈希
and the last chaining variable, we obtain
H t+1 and, similarly, the same thing
我们得到了H t+1，同样的，我们对M'进行同样的计算
happens with M'. By hashing the last
message block, the last chaining variable,
通过计算最后的信息分组和最后的链接变量的哈希
我们得到了H’r+1，我们知道，只要这两个变量是相等的
we obtain H' r+1. And we know
that, since these two values are equal, all
我么就有了一个候选的压缩函数的碰撞
of a sudden we have a candidate collision
for the compression function. Here, let me
这里，我们圈出这个候选的碰撞，这是它的一部分，这是它的另一部分
circle the candidate collision, this is one
part of it and this is the other part of
由于在这两个参数间有一个等式
it. Okay, so we have an equality
between two arguments given to the
把这两个参数给压缩函数，正好产生的相同的值
compression function that happen to
produce the same value. The only way we
我们不获得任何一个碰撞的唯一方法是,这两个参数相等
would not get a collision is if the
arguments happen to be the same. In other
换句话说，这里我们注意到，如果这两个参数不同
words, what we're seeing here is if the
arguments to the compression function are
那么我们就得到了h的一个碰撞，我们写的更精确一些
distinct, then we get a collision for
little h. So let's write it out more
如果Ht不等于H'r或者Mt不等于M'r
precisely: so if H t is not equal to H' r,
or Mt is not equal to M' r,
或者补白区块不同，我们就会得到压缩函数h的一个碰撞
or the padding blocks are distinct, then
we have a collision for the compression
这样的们就完成了，就可以结束了。我们还要继续做的情况是
function h and we're done, we're done and we can stop.
So, the only way we need to continue is if
如果这三个‘或’条件不成立，三个‘或’条件不成立是什么意思呢？
this three-way disjunction doesn't hold.
So what does it mean that this disjunction
我们需要继续工作的唯一情形是，当最后一个变量和倒数第二个变量相等
doesn't hold? well, so the only reason we
need to continue is if the second-to-last
两个信息的最后分组也相同
chaining variables are equal, the last
blocks of the messages are equal and the
并且，两个补白区块也相同，两个补白区块相等是什么意思呢？
two padding blocks are equal. So what does
it mean that the two padding blocks are
还记得被编码在补白区块的信息长度吧
equal? Remember that the message lengths
were encoded in the padding block. So, in
特别的，这意味着M的长度等于M'的长度
particular, this means that the length of M
and the length of M' is the same,
也就是说t是等于r的。所以现在我可以假设t=r。
namely the t is equal to r. So from now on
I can assume t is equal to r. Whenever I
我写r时就等同于我写t。但是现在我们可以对倒数第二个变量应用相同的参数
wrote r, I'm just gonna write t. But now we
can apply exactly the same argument to the
换句话说，H是怎么计算的？
second to last chaining variables. In
other words, how was H t computed? Well
Ht 是通过前一个链接变量Ht-1和倒数第二个的信息分组的哈希计算得来的
H t is computed by hashing the previous
chaining variable, namely H t-1,
相似的，我们可以得到H't
with the second to last message block. And
similarly, H' t was computed, you
注意到我用r代替了t，所以H't是通过通过前一个的链接变量和
notice I replaced r by t, so H' t was
computed by hashing the previous chaining
M' 的倒数第二个的信息分组的哈希得到的
variable along with the second to last
message block of M'. And because
由于这两者相同，所以我们得到了另一个候选的压缩函数的碰撞
these two are equal, now we get another
candidate collision for the compression
换句话说，如果Ht+1不等于Ht-1，或者Mt-1不等于M't-1
function. In other words, if H t+1 is not
equal to H' t-1, or M t-1 is not equal to
那我们就有了一个h的碰撞，那么我们就可以结束了
M' t-1, then basically we
have a collision for h, and we can stop,
现在，我们唯一需要继续的情况是这个条件不存在
we're done. So now, the only case when we
need to continue is if this condition over
也就是说，假设Ht-1等于H't-1
here doesn't hold, namely, so let's suppose
that H t-1 is equal to H' t-1
我们已经知道，Mt 等于M't
and we already know that, let's
see, so M t is equal to M' t and
并且Mt-1等于M't-1。假设这两个条件都成立
M t-1 is equal to M' t-1.
Suppose it so happens that these two
这里你可以看到，我们可以继续迭代了
conditions hold, well, you can see that now
we can continue to iterate. In other
换句话说，我们可以给Ht-1和H't-1使用相同的参数
words, we can now apply exactly the same
argument to H t-1 and H' t-1
然后依次迭代，我们就可以迭代出
and so iterating this again and
again, we can iterate all the way to the
信息的开始。迭代到信息的开始，下面两者之一一定成立：
beginning of the message. Iterate to the
beginning of the message, and one of two
我们找不到任何一个压缩函数的碰撞或者
things must hold, either we find the
collision for the compression function
所有的信息M和M’的所有信息分组都相等
or it so happens that all the message blocks
of M and M' are the same. In other
换句话说，对于所有的i，Mi =M'i。这意味着
words, for all i, M i is equal to M' i.
But this means, because the messages, we'd
由于我们已经证明过这些信息是一样长的，所以M=M’的
reprove the messages are the same length,
this means that M is actually equal to M'.
然而，是和这与你给我的是个碰撞的前提矛盾
But then, this contradicts the fact
that you gave me a collision to begin
换句话说，由于有矛盾，故这不可能发生
with, so, in other words, this condition
over here, can't actually happen because
因为它与M和M'是这个大Merkle-Damgard函数H相碰撞这个事实矛盾
it contradicts the fact that M and M'
are actually a collision for the big
因此，我们必须为这个压缩函数找一碰撞
Merkle-Damgard function H. And, as
a result, this means that we have to find a
既然这样，让我们从信息的最后开始工作
collision for the compression function, so
that, as we work our way from the end of
一直算到信息的开始，在某处我们一定可以找到h的碰撞
the message, all the way to the beginning,
at some point we must find the collision
这基本就完成了我们的证明
for little h. Okay, so this basically
completes the proof of the theorems, I can
我可以在这里写个‘证明完毕’，这就是证明
put a little QED block here, so basically
what this proof is, that if the little
如果压缩函数h是抗碰撞的，那么大Merkle-Damgard函数H
compression function h is collision
resistant, then the big Merkle-Damgard
必须也是抗碰撞的。所以，人们喜欢这个机制的原因是
function H must also be collision
resistant. So, again, the reason why people
这个定理展示了如何构建大的哈希函数
like this construction is it shows that
to construct big hash functions,
只要能构建短输入的压缩就足够了
it suffices to construct just compression
functions for small inputs, and we're
下面我们进入下一章节
gonna do that in the next segment.